This little assistant is already talking
back to me — in two languages. And the
wild part isn't that some AI company made
this. You are going to build it today. Two
tiny files. Never coded before? Perfect.
Let's go.
Most courses make you climb a mountain of
theory before you build anything. We go
the other way — top-down: build something
that works first, learn each piece only
when the project needs it. You use
everything five seconds later, so you stay
hooked.
Meet Muse, your own AI assistant. Today we
build one thing: talking. But almost every
AI product starts right here. Talking,
then remembering, then using tools —
that's an AI agent. Today is step one.
First, check that Node is on your
computer. If a version shows up, you're
ready.
Now make the project. One create-next-app
command spins up an empty workspace. If it
asks questions, just hit Enter.
Step into the folder it made — cd, then
the project name.
Before Muse can think, it borrows a brain
— Claude, by Anthropic. For that you need
one thing: an API key. Honestly, you
wouldn't post your front-door code in a
YouTube comment, right? An API key is the
same — usage gets billed to you. So we
never put it in the code; we keep it in a
secret file, guarded like that front-door
code.
Now the brain. And hey — don't memorize
this code, just copy it from the GitHub
link. Think of this file as a private
room. The API key is only visible in here.
Visitors get the answer and leave; the
real password never walks out. That's what
'server' means.
A brain needs a face. No need to retype
this either — copy it from GitHub. This is
the chat screen: a text box and a Send
button. Hit send, it goes to the brain and
shows the reply.
Time to give Muse its toolkit — npm
install. In a moment, the packages are
added.
Finally, run it — npm run dev. When the
address appears, just open it in your
browser.
Run it, open the address, type 'Hi Muse'…
wait. Did you just see that? A program you
built a minute ago just spoke to you. This
isn't my app anymore — it's yours.
My favorite part — let's break it on
purpose. Remove the key and send: it
doesn't explode. Muse calmly asks for the
key. A developer isn't someone with no
errors — it's someone who got comfortable
with them. An error isn't failure; it's
the computer handing you a hint.
Before we close, say it in your own words:
my app sends a message to a model and
shows the reply. Yesterday you had no AI
app. Today you do. It doesn't have to be
perfect — you built one more thing than
yesterday. That's a developer's win.
But chat a while and you'll notice Muse
rambles. Next episode, we give it a soul
in basically one line. Subscribe, and tell
me in the comments: if your Muse could
take one job off your hands, what would
you give it first? See you in EP1.